Guojie Zhong

PhD candidate, Department of Systems Biology, Columbia University
1130 St. Nicholas Avenue, New York, NY, USA | Phone: (+01)7187305993 | Email: gz2294@cumc.columbia.edu
Website: https://zhongguojie1998.github.io/GuojieZhong/

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research is driven by the ultimate goal to bridge the gap between complex human diseases and effective treatments. To achieve this, I develop biologically-inspired machine learning algorithms that can be applied to high-throughput genomics data to uncover disease mechanisms at genetics, epigenetics, transcriptomics, and protein levels.

EDUCATION

PhD in Systems Biology, Integrated program in cellular, molecular and biomedical sciences

O8/2019 – present

Department of Systems Biology, Columbia University, New York, NY, USA.

Thesis Advisor: Yufeng Shen

Committee: Wendy Chung, Mohammad AlQurashi, David Knowles

Exchange Student in Berkeley Bioscience Study Abroad Program (BBSA) 08/2017 – 12/2017

Department of Integrated Biology, University of California, Berkeley, CA, USA.

Bachelor of Science, Integrated Science Program

09/2015 - 07/2019

Yuanpei College, Peking University, Beijing, China.

Thesis Advisor: Zemin Zhang

Thesis: Reconstruction of cell spatial organization from single-cell RNA sequencing data based on ligand-receptor mediated self-assembly

PUBLICATIONS

(# = co-first author)

Deep Learning and missense variant effect prediction

- ◆ **Zhong, G.**, Zhao, Y., Zhuang, D., Chung, W.K. and Shen, Y. PreMode predicts mode-of-action of missense variants by deep graph representation learning of protein sequence and structural context. *bioRxiv*, 2024.02.20.581321 (2024).
- ◆ Zhao, Y., **Zhong, G.**, Hagen, J., Pan, H., Chung, W.K., and Shen, Y. A probabilistic graphical model for estimating selection coefficient of nonsynonymous variants from human population sequence data. *medRxiv*, 2023.12.11.23299809 (2023).

Statistical genetics and rare genetic diseases analysis

- ◆ **Zhong, G.**, Choi, Y.A. and Shen, Y. VBASS enables integration of single cell gene expression data in Bayesian association analysis of rare variants. *Commun Biol* **6**, 774 (2023).
- ◆ **Zhong, G.**, and Shen, Y. Statistical models of the genetic etiology of congenital heart disease. *Curr Opin Genet Dev* **76**, 101967 (2022).
- ♦ Zhong, G., Ahimaz, P., Edwards, N.A., Hagen, J.J., Faure, C., Lu, Q., Kingma, P., Middlesworth, W., Khlevner, J., El Fiky, M., et al. Identification and validation of candidate risk genes in endocytic vesicular trafficking associated with esophageal atresia and tracheoesophageal fistulas. *HGG Adv* 3, 100107 (2022).
- ◆ Edwards, N., Zhong, G., Ahimaz, P., Kenny, A., Kingma, P., Wells, J., Shen, Y., Chung, W., and Zorn, A. Discovering the Developmental Basis of Trachea-Esophageal Birth Defects: Evidence for Endosome-opathies. *The FASEB Journal* 36 (2022).

Single cell and spatial transcriptomics

- ◆ Su, J., Reynier, J.B., Fu, X., **Zhong, G.**, Jiang, J., Escalante, R.S., Wang, Y., Aparicio, L., Izar, B., Knowles, D.A., and Rabadan, R. Smoother: a unified and modular framework for incorporating structural dependency in spatial omics data. Genome Biol **24**, 291(2023).
- ◆ Ren, X.#, **Zhong, G.**#, Zhang, Q., Zhang, L., Sun, Y., and Zhang, Z. Reconstruction of cell spatial organization from single-cell RNA sequencing data based on ligand-receptor mediated self-assembly. *Cell Res* **30**, 763-778 (2020).
- ◆ Zhang, Q., He, Y., Luo, N., Patel, S.J., Han, Y., Gao, R., Modak, M., Carotta, S., Haslinger, C., Kind, D., Peet G.W., **Zhong**, G., Lu, S., Zhu, W., Mao, Y., Xiao, M., et al. Landscape and Dynamics of Single Immune Cells in Hepatocellular Carcinoma. *Cell* **179**, 829-845 e20 (2019).

CONFERENCES

- ◆ **Zhong, G.**, and Shen, Y. (2023). Predicting mode of action of missense variants by graph representation of protein structural context. *American Society of Human Genetics 2023 Annual Meeting, Washington, D.C.*
- ◆ **Zhong, G.**, and Shen, Y. (2022). Representation of missense variants for predicting modes of action. *Machine Learning in Structural Biology, Workshop at the 36th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems*.
- ◆ **Zhong, G.**, Choi, Y.A., and Shen, Y. (2022). Integration of gene expression data in Bayesian association analysis of rare variants. *American Society of Human Genetics 2022 Annual Meeting*, Los Angelas, CA.
- ◆ **Zhong, G.**, Wang, J., He, S. and Fu, X. (2021). Towards better understanding of developmental disorders from integration of spatial single-cell transcriptomics and epigenomics. *The 2021 ICML Workshop on Computational Biology, Virtual meeting.*

AWARDS

THE	
Dean's fellowship, Graduate School of Arts and Science, Columbia University	2019
2014-2015 academic year Outstanding Freshman Scholarship, Peking University	2015
The 28th National Olympiad in Chemistry in Provinces, 1st prize, Zhejiang Province, China	2014

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCES

Research Assistant 08/2019 – present

Department of Systems Biology

Columbia University Irving Medical Center, New York, NY, USA

Research Assistant 03/2017 – 07/2019

Biomedical Pioneering Innovation Center (BIOPIC)

Peking University, Beijing, China

PhD Student, Department of Systems Biology, Columbia University